Guide to the Committee on African Studies records, 1965-1976 UA.07.04.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Committee on African Studies records
1965-1976.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for International Studies. Committee on African Studies
UA.07.04.0001
1.5 Linear Feet
The Committee on African Studies formed in 1965 as part of the Center for International Studies at Duke University. The committee was composed of faculty from the departments of history, political science, anthropology, and economics. Its mission included supporting research in Africa, publishing articles and sponsoring lectures on African studies, and developing African studies curricula for middle school and high school students. Records date from 1967 to 1976 and consist of correspondence, papers and proposals, course materials, reprints, and sound recordings. The Committee's work focused on cultures including the Dan, Mbuti, Somali, and Zulu. The bulk of the material relates to the African Curriculum Development Project conducted in cooperation with the North Carolina Department of Public Instruction, and publication of the series Africa Sketches. English.
1,000 items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the director of the office of use and the University Archivist is required for use.
Acquisitions Information
This collection consists of material acquired in accession numbers: 68-339 from the Committee on African Studies; 76-159; and 82-124, from the Center for International Studies.
Historical Note
The Committee on African Studies was formed in 1965 as part of the Center for International Studies. The committee was composed of faculty from the departments of history, political science, anthropology, and economics. Its mission included connecting students and faculty with grants and research opportunities in Africa, publishing a reprint series of selected articles on African studies, and sponsoring lectures and colloquia by noted Africanists, as well as a faculty exchange program with Makere University College. They also were involved with the North Carolina Department of Public Instruction in developing African studies curriculum for junior high and high school students. Directors of the Committee included J. Harris Proctor, and Gerald Hartwig.
Scope and Content Note
These records were produced by the Committee on African Studies in the course of their activities. Materials are present from 1967 to 1976. The records consist of correspondence, papers and proposals, course materials, reprints, and sound recordings. The bulk of the material relates to the African Curriculum Development Project.
Related Material
African Profiles: Mbuti, Somali, Zulu
University Archives, Duke University [Call number: 967.7 A258 A258 1975]
Center for International Studies Records
University Archives, Duke University
Committee on International Studies Records
University Archives, Duke University
Africa -- Study and teaching; Africa -- Social life and customs; Dan (African people); Mbuti (African people); Somalia -- Study and teaching; Somalis; Zulu (African people); Sound recordings; North Carolina. Department of Public Instruction; African Curriculum Development Project (Duke University); Duke University. Center for International Studies. Committee on African Studies; Duke University. Center for International Studies. Committee on African Studies
- Correspondence, 1973-1976
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains general correspondence from the Director's office relating to the function and projects of the Committee.
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Seminars, 1967.
  Two reels of sound recordings documenting the "Recent Developments in Nigeria Seminar" make up this series. Participants included committee members, faculty from nearby universities, and other scholars.
  - Recent Developments in Nigeria Seminar, 1967, Reels 1-2 (Box 1)
- African Curriculum Development Project, 1973-1976
  Arrangement note
  Arrangement: alphabetical by subject
  This series contains material relating to the project undertaken by the Committee and the North Carolina Department of Public Instruction to develop supplementary classroom units and materials for inclusion into junior high and high school social studies curricula. The project was supported by a National Endowment for Humanities grant. In 1973 fourteen North Carolina teachers came to the Duke campus for an eight-week session to prepare teaching units and materials. The program was repeated in the summer of 1974. Cultures focused on by group include the Dan, Mbuti, Somali, and Zulu. The subject files in this series contain correspondence with participants regarding their individual projects, as well as evaluations of how the teaching units were received in the classroom. Other materials include the grant proposal, some background papers on African studies in the public schools, budgets, and correspondence relating to the publication of several of the units prepared during the summer session.
  - Books, Harry K., 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Brooks, Marolyn, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Budget, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Consultants and Lecturers, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Course Materials, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--General, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Crowley, Chris, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Dan Unit, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Delancey, Mark, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Forshee, Katie, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Gaffney, Harry, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Gaige, Frederick, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Grant Proposal, National Endowment for the Humanities, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Hutchins, Mary Lee, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Leigh, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Larson, Emilie, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Lennon, Alma, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, Pamela, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Nelson, Fred, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - O'Neal, Richard, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Paper, "Focusing an African Curriculum," 1973 (Box 1)
  - Proposal for the Publication of African Materials for use in the Public Schools, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Publicity, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Rupard, Daphne, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Thomas, Elma, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Vogler, Carol, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Voss, Mary Jane, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
- Africa Sketches, 1973-1976
  The records in this series chronicle the publication of Africa Sketches, a series of nine short biographical sketches of contemporary Africans written for secondary school students. Committee director Gerald Hartwig served as General Editor for the series. The idea for the books grew out of the work of the African Curriculum Development Project.
  Materials include correspondence with the authors and publisher, as well as some sample illustrations.
  - Abdelrasoul, Omer, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Azvedo, Mario, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Brown, James, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Buchanan, Carole, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--General, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Crane, Louise, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - DeLancey, Mark, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Dubisch, Joyce, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Ferguson, Henry, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Ferraro, Gary, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Greenstein, Lewis, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Illustrations, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Larson, Thomas, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Spitzer, Leo, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Reprints, 1965-1973
  Arrangement: chronological
  This series contains issues of the reprints series published by the Committee. These were articles written by committee members or at its behest. This series does not contain a complete run of the issues. Issue Nos. 13, 19, 20, and 21 are missing. It appears that No. 22 is the last issue published.
  - Nos. 1-12, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Nos. 14-18, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - No. 22, 1973 (Box 1)